Tristan RH Goodbody

REMOTE SENSING OF FORESTS SPECIALIST

University of British Columbia, Vancouver

□ +604 992 1327 | ☑ goodbody.t@gmail.com | ☑ 0000-0002-6894-7925 | ☑ tgoodbody | У Goodbody |

About me

I have 7 years of experience working with remote sensing data in the context of forest resources management and inventory. During that time I have successfully defended my PhD, collaborated with multiple levels of government, private industry, and academia, acted as a mentor for students of all levels of post-secondary education, and produced high impact science that continues to be operationalized. My work in developing a robust open-source tool for structurally guided sampling has received international and interdisciplinary acclaim and is being actively developed to continue to enhance forest inventories.

Experience

Post-Doctoral Fellow Vancouver, BC

FACULTY OF FOREST RESOURCES MANAGEMENT (UBC)

June 2019 - Present

- Assessment of wood attributes using remote sensing (AWARE) & Canadian Wood Fibre Center Forest Innovation Program.
 - Initialized and maintained a two year international committee (academic, government, industry) to develop an open source sampling R
 package
 - Maintain the sgsR package on CRAN and GitHub.
 - Consulted with private industry and government to process and analyze lidar and digital photogrammetric data
 - Collaborated with Canadian federal government to generate digital photogrammetric benchmarks for landscape level inventories
 - Mentored graduate students in remote sensing procesing, analytics, scientific communication, & writing
 - Contributed to multiple indepth literature reviews of remote sensing forest inventory practices and future directions
 - Modelled potential human-wildife interactions, culturally important plant species, and using species distribution models
 - Developed lidar processing and analysis frameworks to enhance forest inventory knowledge
 - Published in high impact journals with high rate of citations

Teaching assistant Vancouver, BC

FACULTY OF FOREST RESOURCES MANAGEMENT (UBC)

May 2015 - March 2019

- Leading & supervising applied exercises to guide student knowledge of remote sensing concepts.
 - FRST 443 Remote sensing for ecosystem management; FRST 521 Advanced earth observation and image processing
 - Guided students to success in written and oral submissions
 - Guest lectured on advanced remote sensing systems and data processing techniques
 - Developed graduate labs and evaluated research proposals & assignments

Planning Forester Intern - Co-op

Chetwynd, BC

CHETWYND FOREST INDUSTRIES - WEST FRASER MILLS LTD.

May 2014 - December 2014

- Working in a team and individually to implement West Fraser Management objectives.
 - Site plan preparation
 - Harvest planning & layout
 - Silviculture assessments and reforestation quality inspections
 - Post-fire salvage planning and management
 - Forest appraisals

Planning Forester Intern - Co-op

Williams Lake, BC

ALEX FRASER RESEARCH FOREST (UBC)

May 2013 - September 2013

- Implemented planning and management perscriptions.
 - Road & timber layout
 - Timber cruising
 - Volume determination
 - Avian habitat assessments

Education

University of British Columbia

Vancouver, BC

PHD REMOTE SENSING OF FORESTS

May 2015 - March 2019

· Assessing the role of digital aerial photogrammetry for characterizing forest structure and enhancing forest inventories

University of British Columbia

Vancouver, BC

BSc Natural Resources Conservation (Hons.& Co-op)

September 2010 - January 2015

- · Science and Management Major.
 - Cons 330: Conservation Policy
 - FRST 443: Remote Sensing Of Ecosystem Management

Skills_

Data Science R (Advanced), LAStools, lidR, ENVI, ARC/QGIS, ArcPy, Developed sgsR package

Research Forest modelling, inventory analysis, lidar processing, digital aerial photogrammetry, raster & vector analysis

Collaboration Extensive work with international academic, government, and industry representatives

Writing Scientific publications, public reports, funding grants, reproducible reporting (Rmarkdown, bookdown)

Communication Confident public speaker, effective graphic design (Illustrator/inDesign)

Languages English/Spanish (bilingual)

Awards

PhD Funding Vancouver, BC

NSERC PGSD 2018

PhD Funding Vancouver, BC

HARRY G. SMITH SCHOLARSHIP

Peer-Reviewed Publications

- 1. Achim, A., Moreau, G., Coops, N. C., Axelson, J. N., Barrette, J., Bédard, S., Byrne, K. E., Caspersen, J., Dick, A. R., D'Orangeville, L.others. (2022). The changing culture of silviculture. *Forestry*, *95*(2), 143–152.
- 2. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Srivastava, V., Parsons, B., Kearney, S. P., Rickbeil, G. J., & Stenhouse, G. B. (2021). Mapping recreation and tourism use across grizzly bear recovery areas using social network data and maximum entropy modelling. *Ecological Modelling*, 440, 109377.
- 3. Toit, F. du, Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., Stoehr, M., & El-Kassaby, Y. A. (2021). Deriving internal crown geometric features of douglas-fir from airborne laser scanning in a realized-gain trial. *Forestry: An International Journal of Forest Research*, 94(3), 442–454.
- 4. Fu, X., Zhang, Z., Cao, L., Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., Liu, H., Shen, X., & Wu, X. (2021). Assessment of approaches for monitoring forest structure dynamics using bi-temporal digital aerial photogrammetry point clouds. *Remote Sensing of Environment*, 255, 112300.
- 5. Tompalski, P., Coops, N. C., White, J. C., Goodbody, T. R., Hennigar, C. R., Wulder, M. A., Socha, J., & Woods, M. E. (2021). Estimating changes in forest attributes and enhancing growth projections: A review of existing approaches and future directions using airborne 3D point cloud data (feb, 10.1007/s40725-021-00135-w, 2021). *Current Forestry Reports*, 7(1), 25–30.
- 6. Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., Queinnec, M., Luther, J. E., Bolton, D. K., White, J. C., Wulder, M. A., Lier, O. R. van, & Hermosilla, T. (2021). Modelling lidar-derived estimates of forest attributes over space and time: A review of approaches and future trends. *Remote Sensing of Environment*, 260, 112477.
- 7. Kearney, S. P., Larsen, T. A., Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., & Stenhouse, G. B. (2021). Characterizing off-highway road use with remote-sensing, social media and crowd-sourced data: An application to grizzly bear (ursus arctos) habitat. *Remote Sensing*, *13*(13), 2547.
- 8. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Luther, J. E., Tompalski, P., Mulverhill, C., Frizzle, C., Fournier, R., Furze, S., & Herniman, S. (2021). Airborne laser scanning for quantifying criteria and indicators of sustainable forest management in canada. *Canadian Journal of Forest Research*, 51(7), 972–985.
- 9. Coops, N. C., Achim, A., Arp, P., Bater, C. W., Caspersen, J. P., Cote, J.-F., Dech, J. P., Dick, A. R., Ewijk, K. van, Fournier, R. others. (2021). Advances in the application of remote sensing for forest information needs in canada: Lessons learned from a national collaboration of academic, industry, and government stakeholders. *Forestry Chronicle*, 97(2), 127–147.
- 10. Goodbody, T. R., White, J. C., Coops, N. C., & LeBoeuf, A. (2021). Benchmarking acquisition parameters for digital aerial photogrammetric data for forest inventory applications: Impacts of image overlap and resolution. *Remote Sensing of Environment*, 265, 112677.

- Czekajlo, A., Coops, N. C., & Goodbody, T. R. (2021). Untangling the effect of urban vegetation type and structure on spectrally unmixed greenness. Remote Sensing Letters, 12(12), 1216-1226.
- 12. Coops, N. C., Achim, A., Arp, P., Bater, C. W., Caspersen, J. P., Côté, J.-F., Dech, J. P., Dick, A. R., Ewijk, K. van, Fournier, R. others. (2021). Advancing the application of remote sensing for forest information needs in canada: Lessons learned from a national collaboration of university, industrial and government stakeholders. The Forestry Chronicle, 97(2), 109–126.
- 13. Toit, F. du, Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., El-Kassaby, Y. A., Stoehr, M., Turner, D., & Lucieer, A. (2020). Characterizing variations in growth characteristics between douglas-fir with different genetic gain levels using airborne laser scanning. Trees, 34(3), 649-664.
- 14. Goodbody, T. R., Tompalski, P., Coops, N. C., White, J. C., Wulder, M. A., & Sanelli, M. (2020). Uncovering spatial and ecological variability in gap size frequency distributions in the canadian boreal forest. Scientific Reports, 10(1), 1–12.
- 15. Xu, Z., Shen, X., Cao, L., Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., Zhong, T., Zhao, W., Sun, Q., Ba, S., Zhang, Z.others. (2020). Tree species classification using UAS-based digital aerial photogrammetry point clouds and multispectral imageries in subtropical natural forests. International Journal of Applied Earth Observation and Geoinformation, 92, 102173.
- 16. Goodbody, T. R., Tompalski, P., Coops, N. C., Hopkinson, C., Treitz, P., & Ewijk, K. van. (2020). Forest inventory and diversity attribute modelling using structural and intensity metrics from multi-spectral airborne laser scanning data. Remote Sensing, 12(13), 2109.
- Roussel, J.-R., Auty, D., Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., Meador, A. S., Bourdon, J.-F., De Boissieu, F., & Achim, A. (2020). lidR: An r package for analysis of airborne laser scanning (ALS) data. Remote Sensing of Environment, 251, 112061.
- 18. Chadwick, A. J., Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Hervieux, A., Bater, C. W., Martens, L. A., White, B., & Röeser, D. (2020). Automatic delineation and height measurement of regenerating conifer crowns under leaf-off conditions using UAV imagery. Remote Sensing, 12(24), 4104.
- 19. Gómez, C., Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Álvarez-Taboada, F., & Sanz-Ablanedo, E. (2020). Forest ecosystem monitoring using unmanned aerial systems. In *Unmanned aerial remote sensing* (pp. 173–196). CRC Press.
- 20. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., & White, J. C. (2019). Digital aerial photogrammetry for updating area-based forest inventories: A review of opportunities, challenges, and future directions. Current Forestry Reports, 5(2), 55–75.
- 21. Goodbody, T. R. H. (2019). Assessing the role of digital aerial photogrammetry for characterizing forest structure and enhancing forest inventories [PhD thesis]. University of British Columbia.
- 22. Nuijten, R. J., Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., & Pelletier, G. (2019). Examining the multi-seasonal consistency of individual tree segmentation on deciduous stands using digital aerial photogrammetry (DAP) and unmanned aerial systems (UAS). Remote Sensing, 11(7),
- 23. Coops, N. C., Goodbody, T. R., & Cao, L. (2019). Four steps to extend drone use in research. Nature Publishing Group.
- 24. Yancho, J. M. M., Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Goodbody, T. R., & Plowright, A. (2019). Fine-scale spatial and spectral clustering of UAVacquired digital aerial photogrammetric (DAP) point clouds for individual tree crown detection and segmentation. Ieee Journal of Selected Topics in Applied Earth Observations and Remote Sensing, 12(10), 4131–4148.
- 25. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Hermosilla, T., Tompalski, P., & Crawford, P. (2018). Assessing the status of forest regeneration using digital aerial photogrammetry and unmanned aerial systems. International Journal of Remote Sensing, 39(15-16), 5246-5264.
- 26. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Hermosilla, T., Tompalski, P., McCartney, G., & MacLean, D. A. (2018). Digital aerial photogrammetry for assessing cumulative spruce budworm defoliation and enhancing forest inventories at a landscape-level. Isprs Journal of Photogrammetry and Remote Sensing, 142, 1–11.
- Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Hermosilla, T., Tompalski, P., & Pelletier, G. (2018). Vegetation phenology driving error variation in digital aerial photogrammetrically derived terrain models. Remote Sensing, 10(10), 1554.
- 28. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Tompalski, P., Crawford, P., & Day, K. J. (2017). Updating residual stem volume estimates using ALS-and UAV-acquired stereo-photogrammetric point clouds. International Journal of Remote Sensing, 38(8-10), 2938-2953.
- 29. Goodbody, T. R., Coops, N. C., Marshall, P. L., Tompalski, P., & Crawford, P. (2017). Unmanned aerial systems for precision forest inventory purposes: A review and case study. The Forestry Chronicle, 93(1), 71-81.

Presentations_

UBC - UTAS Workshop

ForestSAT Berlin, Germany September 2022

SGSR: STRUCTURALLY GUIDED SAMPLING

Hobart, Australia

SGSR: A STRUCTURALLY GUIDED SAMPLING TOOLBOX FOR LIDAR-BASED FOREST INVENTORIES

April 2022

AWARE E-lecture Series	Online
DIGITAL PHOTOGRAMMETRIC APPLICATIONS TO ENHANCED FOREST INVENTORY	October 2019
Silvilaser	Foz de Iguazu, Brazil
Uncovering spatial and ecological variability in gap size frequency distributions in the Canadian boreal forest	October 2019
CIF-IFC Workshop	Edmonton, AB
EXAMINING POTENTIAL APPLICATIONS OF UAS AND DIGITAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY FOR VARIOUS FOREST MANAGEMENT PURPOSES	April 2019
FRI Forest Practitioners Conference	Edmonton, AB
ASSESSING THE STATUS OF FOREST REGENERATION USING DIGITAL AERIAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY AND UNMANNED AERIAL SYSTEMS	October 2018
AWARE Instructional Sessions	Kamloops, BC
LIDAR THEORY, PROCESSING AND IMPLEMENTATION WORKSHOP	February 2018
AWARE Instructional Sessions	Huntsville, ON
LIDAR THEORY, PROCESSING AND IMPLEMENTATION WORKSHOP	October 2017
AWARE Instructional Sessions	Kapuskasing, ON
LIDAR THEORY, PROCESSING AND IMPLEMENTATION WORKSHOP	October 2017
AWARE Instructional Sessions	Quesnel, BC
LIDAR THEORY, PROCESSING AND IMPLEMENTATION WORKSHOP	October 2017
Silvilaser	Blacksburg, USA
Assessing the capacity of DAP to enhance inventory knowledge of Spruce Budworm affected forests	November 2017
Symposium on Systems and Analysis in Forest Resources	Suquamish, USA
UPDATING AIRBORNE LASER SCANNING EFI METRICS USING UAV ACQUIRED DAP POINT CLOUDS	August 2017
UAV and Remote Sensing Workshop	Nanjing, China
UAV and Digital Photogrammetry for forestry purposes	July 2017
Assessment of Wood Attributes for Remote Sensing AGM	Edmunston, NB
Assessing the capacity of DAP to enhance inventory knowledge of Spruce Budworm affected forests	May 2017
ForestSAT	Santiago, Chile
MODELLING RESIDUAL STAND VOLUME USING UNMANNED AERIAL VEHICLES AND DIGITAL AERIAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY	November 2016
FP Innovations UAV Workshop	Courtney, BC
UAVS AND THE UNIVERSITY OF BRITISH COLUMBIA	October 2016
Canadian Remote Sensing Symposium	Winnepeg, MB
MODELLING RESIDUAL STAND VOLUME USING UNMANNED AERIAL VEHICLES AND DIGITAL AERIAL PHOTOGRAMMETRY	June 2016
Southern Interior Silviculture Committee	Kamloops, BC
DAP POINT CLOUDS ACQUIRED FROM UNMANNED AERIAL SYSTEMS (UAS) FOR ENHANCING FOREST INVENTORIES	February 2016
Alex Fraser Research Forest Proof of Concept Workshop	Williams Lake, BC
RESEARCH IN USE OF DRONES TO UPDATE LIDAR FOREST INVENTORIES. LIDAR HIGH RESOLUTION INVENTORY FOR THE IDF	June 2015